{
  "paper": "Paper 2",
  "term": "December",
  "year": 2024,
  "subject": "Social Studies",
  "language": "English",
  "questions": [
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q31",
      "question": "Which of the following Kingdoms was established by Kadamba Mayurasharman?",
      "options": [
        "Madhya Pradesh",
        "Karnataka",
        "Rajasthan",
        "Gujarat"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Karnataka",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q32",
      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct about planets?",
      "options": [
        "All (A), (B) and (C)",
        "Only (A)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "Only (B) and (C)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (A)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q33",
      "question": "The most important factor that influences the distribution of temperature on earth is:",
      "options": [
        "Crowded high rise buildings",
        "Insolation or Incoming Solar Radiation",
        "Seasons",
        "Asphalt of roads"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Insolation or Incoming Solar Radiation",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q34",
      "question": "Consider the following statements on the non-Brahman movement and choose the valid option: \n(a) The movement came from non-Brahman castes that had acquired access to education. \n(b) The movement argued that the Aryans were the indigenous people. \n(c) The movement came from non-Brahman castes with wealth and influence.",
      "options": [
        "Only (b) is valid.",
        "Only (a) and (c) are valid.",
        "Only (b) and (c) are valid.",
        "Only (c) is valid."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (a) and (c) are valid.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q35",
      "question": "Who among the following worked with leather workers in Central India and also started Satnami Movement?",
      "options": [
        "U.B. Phadke",
        "Jyotirao Phule",
        "Ghasidas",
        "Haridas Thakur"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ghasidas",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q36",
      "question": "What type of winds are Land and Sea breeze?",
      "options": [
        "Permanent winds",
        "Cyclone",
        "Local winds",
        "Seasonal winds"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Local winds",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q37",
      "question": "While teaching in a Social Science class, a student asks you - \"How can we measure the distance between longitudes on the Equator? What is the correct answer for such a calculation?\"",
      "options": [
        "Dividing the double length of the Equator by 90.",
        "Dividing the total length of the Equator by 180.",
        "Dividing the total length of the Equator by 360.",
        "Dividing the half length of the Equator by 360."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Dividing the total length of the Equator by 360.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q38",
      "question": "Which of the following is the correct sequence of rock cycle ?",
      "options": [
        "Igneous Rock, Magma, Metamorphic Rock",
        "Sedimentary Rock, Metamorphic Rock, Magma",
        "Igneous Rock, Metamorphic Rock, Sedimentary Rock",
        "Magma, Metamorphic Rock, Sedimentary Rock"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sedimentary Rock, Metamorphic Rock, Magma",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q39",
      "question": "Match the following and choose the appropriate option.\n (a) Punch marked coins                (i) Stamped glazed pottery\n (b) Northern Black polished ware      (ii) Tall double handled jars\n (c) Amphorae                          (iii) Extremely fine pottery   \n (d) Arretine ware                      (iv) Stamped with symbols using dyes\n",
      "options": [
        "(a) - (iv), (b) - (i), (c) - (iii), (d) - (ii)",
        "(a) - (iv), (b) - (i), (c) - (ii), (d) - (iii)",
        "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)",
        "(a) - (iv), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iii), (d) - (i)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(a) - (iv), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q40",
      "question": "Read the statements (A) and (R) carefully and choose the correct option.\n(A) : Using resources carefully and giving them time to get renewed is called resource conservation.\n(R) : Balancing the need to use resources and also conserve them for the future is called sustainable\ndevelopment.\n",
      "options": [
        "(A) is false but (R) is true.",
        "Both the statements (A) and (R) are true and (R) explains (A).",
        "Both the statements (A) and (R) are true but (R) does not explain (A).",
        "(A) is true but (R) is false. "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both the statements (A) and (R) are true but (R) does not explain (A).",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q41",
      "question": "Which one of the following is incorrect ?",
      "options": [
        "The dissatisfaction with British rule intensified in 1870s and 1880s.",
        "The Arms Act was passed in 1878, disallowing Indians from possessing arms.",
        "The Vernacular Press Act was passed in 1880, to support the Government.",
        "In 1883, there was a furore over the attempt by the Government to introduce the Ibert Bill. "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The Vernacular Press Act was passed in 1880, to support the Government.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q42",
      "question": "Consider the following statements about grasslands and choose the correct option.\n(A) Climate plays an important role in the formation of grasslands.\n(B) Annual rainfall is moderate in Prairies while velds could face drought in winter months.\n(C) The vegetation cover is sparse in Velds.\n(D) Velds lie in the Northern Hemisphere while Prairies in the Southern Hemisphere.\n",
      "options": [
        "All (A), (B), (C) and (D) are correct.",
        "Only (A), (B) and (C) are correct.",
        "Only (B), (C) and (D) are correct.",
        "Only (A), (O) and (D) are correct. "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (A), (B) and (C) are correct.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q43",
      "question": "According to the Uttaramerur inscription, who could become a member of a Sabha ?\n(A) The owners of land from which land revenue is collected.\n(B) They should be between 25 and 70 years of age.\n(C) They should have their own houses.\n(D) They should have knowledge of the Vedas.\n",
      "options": [
        "Only (A), (C) and (D)",
        " Only (A)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "Only (A) and (D)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q44",
      "question": "_____ refers to a situation where a person does not have resources and opportunities that are available to other persons.",
      "options": [
        "Dispossession",
        "Hierarchy",
        "Diversification",
        "Inequality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Inequality",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q45",
      "question": "Which of the following agricultural practices are correctly matched with their descriptions? \n(A) Subsistence Farming - Practiced to meet the needs of farmer's own family \n(B) Intensive Subsistence Agriculture - Prevalent in thickly populated areas \n(C) Shifting Cultivation - People and animals move from place to place",
      "options": [
        "All (A), (B) and (C)",
        "(A) and (B)",
        "(B) and (C)",
        "(A) and (C)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(A) and (B)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q46",
      "question": "Read the statements (A) and (R) and choose the appropriate option.\n(A) : Raja Rammohan Roy founded a reform association known as the Brahmo Sabha in Calcutta.\n(R) : He felt that changes were necessary in society and unjust practices needed to be done away with.",
      "options": [
        "Both (A) and (R) are false.",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
        "(A) is true but (R) is false."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q47",
      "question": "Match the following and choose the appropriate option.\n\nA B\n\n(a) Grihapatis (i) Landless Labourers\n\n(b) Shrenis (i) Independent farmers\n\n(c) Adimai (iii) Coastal Settlement\n\n(d) Arikamedu (iv) Craft persons\n\n",
      "options": [
        " (a) - (ii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (i), (d) - (iii)",
        "(a) - (iv), (b) - (i), (c) - (iii), (d) - (ii)",
        " (a) - (i), (b) - (ii), (c) - (iv), (d) - (iii)",
        " (a) - (iii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (ii), (d) - (i)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q48",
      "question": "World Environment Day is celebrated every year on which one of the following days?",
      "options": [
        "5th August",
        "5th May",
        "5th June",
        "5th July"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "5th June",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q49",
      "question": "Which of the following is true about common property resources? \n(A) These are owned by government. \n(B) These are owned by private companies. \n(C) These are owned by communities.",
      "options": [
        "Only (A) and (C)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "Only (B)",
        "Only (B) and (C)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q50",
      "question": "Maps can be best used for .",
      "options": [
        "Marking places where people have lived at different points in history",
        "Arranging sequence of events in history",
        "Elaborating on the most important events in history",
        "Studying lives of people living in different times in a logical sequence "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q51",
      "question": "Which of the following statements are true about the development of cotton industries in the late 18th and early 19th century colonised India ?\n(a) Indian textile industry had to compete with British textiles in the European and American markets.\n(b) British market was now available for Indian textiles.\n(c) Exporting textile goods to England became increasingly difficult.\n(d) Bengal weavers were worst hit as English and European companies stopped buying Indian\n",
      "options": [
        "(c) and (d) only",
        "(@) (¢) and (d) only",
        "(b), (c) and (d) only",
        "(a) and (b) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(@) (¢) and (d) only",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q52",
      "question": "Consider the following statements (A) and (R) and choose the correct option.\n(A) : The Prairies are also known as the ‘Granaries of the world’.\n(R) : Scientific methods of cultivation and use of tractors, harvesters and combines has made South Africa a surplus food producer.",
      "options": [
        "Both (A) and (R) are false",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
        "(A) is true but (R) is false"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q53",
      "question": "Diversity came with something new and different due to ________.",
      "options": [
        "Homogeneous population",
        "Intermixing of cultures",
        "Genetic composition",
        "Similarities and identical traits"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Intermixing of cultures",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q54",
      "question": "Reservation of seats in legislation and in Government jobs was granted by the Indian Constitution to:\n(A) Compensate for low grades and marks scored in School and University examinations, because of which people were not able to compete.\n (B) Compensate for years of historical suppression and educational deprivation.\n (C) Appease people for political support and rally as vote banks.",
      "options": [
        "Both (B) and (C)",
        "Only (A)",
        "Only (B)",
        "Both (A) and (C)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (B)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q55",
      "question": "Read the statements (A) and (R) considering the art forms in colonial India. \nAssertion (A) : Colonial rule introduced several new art forms, styles and techniques. \nReason (R) : These were creatively adapted by Indian artists for local patrons and markets. Choose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        "Both (A) and (R) are false.",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
        "(A) is true but (R) is false."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q56",
      "question": "Neolithic sites are different than Palaeolithic sites because of the following :\n(i) Mortars and pestles were used for grinding grains.\n(ii) Pots were used for cooking food.\n(iii) Cloth was woven using different kinds of material.\n(iv) Use of stone tools began.\nChoose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        "(0), (i) and (iv) only",
        "(©) and (ii) only",
        "(i), (ii) and (iii) only",
        "(i) and (iv) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(i), (ii) and (iii) only",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q57",
      "question": "Read the given Assertion (A) and Reason (R) statements and choose the appropriate option.\nAssertion (A) : By the late 19\" century, the craft of iron smelting declined and in most villages, furnaces fell into disuse.\nReason (R) : The iron smelters had to pay a very high tax to the Forest Department that reduced their income.\nChoose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        "Both (A) and (R) are false.",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
        "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
        "(A) is true but (R) is false."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q58",
      "question": "Who among the following are elected members of the Local Governments ?\n(A) Ward member \n(B) Panchayat President\n(C) Secretary \n(D) Ward Councillor\n",
      "options": [
        "(A), (B) and (D) only",
        "(A) and (B) only",
        "(A) and (D) only",
        "(A), (B) and (C) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q59",
      "question": "On which of the following dates Gandhiji asked the Indian people to observe a day of non-violent opposition to the ‘Rowlatt Act’?",
      "options": [
        "6 December 1919",
        "6 April 1919",
        "13 April 1919",
        "15 December 1919"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "6 April 1919",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q60",
      "question": "When it is 1:00 p.m. at Greenwich, what time will it be at 60° West and 60° East respectively?",
      "options": [
        "9:00 p.m. and 5:00 a.m.",
        "5:00 p.m. and 9:00 a.m.",
        "9:00 a.m. and 5:00 p.m.",
        "5:00 a.m. and 9:00 p.m."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "9:00 a.m. and 5:00 p.m.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q61",
      "question": "Consider the statements (A) and (B) and choose the correct option of the following.\nStatement (A) : Summative assessment monitors the learners progress throughout the teaching-\nlearning process.\nStatement (B) : Formative assessment is conducted at the end of the course.",
      "options": [
        "(A) is false but (B) is true.",
        "Both (A) and (B) are true.",
        "Both (A) and (B) are false.",
        "(A) is true but (B) is false."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (A) and (B) are false.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q62",
      "question": "Which of the following questions promote critical thinking ?\n(A) What are the different ways through which the Government can take steps to provide\nhealthcare for all ? Discuss.\n(B) Examine the statement : As compared to Amazon, pollution in river Ganga will affect human\nlife greatly.\n(C) Differentiate between the physiography of Brazil and India.\n(D) Describe important features of Himalayas.\n(E) What was the role of the Zamindar in Mughal administration ?\n",
      "options": [
        "Only (B), (C), (D) and (E)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "Only (B) and (C)",
        "Only (A), (B), (C) and (D) "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (A) and (B)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q63",
      "question": "Select the reason behind the low wages paid for agricultural labourers.",
      "options": [
        "They are satisfied with wages prevailing in the market.",
        "They are not skilled.",
        "They depend on land owners for a regular work.",
        "Most of them do not have their own land. "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "They depend on land owners for a regular work.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q64",
      "question": "Social Science curricular activities can be made more engaging for students by .",
      "options": [
        "reducing critical thinking and discussion in favour of lectures.",
        "incorporating technology and multimedia resources.",
        "focusing only on the most important historical events and figures.",
        "emphasizing memorization of facts and figures. "
      ],
      "correct_answer": "incorporating technology and multimedia resources.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q65",
      "question": "Match the following and choose the correct option.\nA B\n(A) Narration charts (i) steps in a process\n(B) Relationship charts (ii) data in the form of table\n(C) Flow charts (iii) historical development\n(D) Tabulation charts (iv) show cause-and-effect relationships\n",
      "options": [
        "(A)-(ii), (B)-(iii), (C)-(iv), (D)-(i)",
        " (A)-(iii), (B)-(iv), (C)-(i), (D)-(ii)",
        "(A)-(iv), (B)-(ii), (C)-(i), (D)-(iii)",
        "(A)-(iv), (B)-(iii), (C)-(ii), (D)-(i)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": " (A)-(iii), (B)-(iv), (C)-(i), (D)-(ii)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q66",
      "question": "The Independence of Judiciary implies :",
      "options": [
        "the judiciary can work under the pressure of legislature, if required.",
        "the legislature and the executive cannot interfere in the work of the judiciary.",
        "the judiciary can direct the legislature to frame appropriate laws.",
        "the judiciary can direct the executive to implement the laws properly."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the legislature and the executive cannot interfere in the work of the judiciary.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q67",
      "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the nature of Social Science ?\n(A) Social Science is a dynamic subject that generates debate and discussion.\n(B) In Social Science only individual human relations are considered and not the accounts of individual actions.\n(C) Social Science is primarily interdisciplinary subject with a focus on discovery and experimentation.\n(D) The scope of Social Science is very narrow and hence it is fit to teach it only at the primary level.\n",
      "options": [
        "(A) and (B) only",
        "(A) and (C) only",
        "(©) and (D) only",
        "(A), (B) and (C) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(A) and (C) only",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q68",
      "question": "Sixty-Percent weightage is given by the teacher to open-ended questions in a Social Science question\npaper. Which skill does the teacher want to test among students through this strategy ?\n(A) Writing skills only\n(B) Intrapersonal skills\n(C) Logical thinking and creative skills\n(D) Application and presentation skills\n",
      "options": [
        "(B), (C) and (D) only",
        "(A) and (B) only",
        "(C) and (D) only",
        "(A), (B) and (C) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(C) and (D) only",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q69",
      "question": "Which of the following aspect is considered in the Right to Education Act, 2009 as part of evaluation\nprocedures ?\n(A) Confirm with the values enshrined in the Indian Constitution\n(B) Examination should involve mainly summative assessment\n(C) Development of the physical abilities of learners to the fullest extent\n(D) Examinations are conducted within the school premises\n",
      "options": [
        "(A) and (C) only",
        "(A), (B) and (C) only",
        "(A), (C) and (D) only",
        "(A) and (B) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q70",
      "question": "Read the statements (A) and (B) and choose the appropriate option.\nStatement (A) : Contemporary challenges to the principle of a democratic society are conflicts such as those between individual rights and social responsibilities.\nStatement (B) : Within a social science classroom, conflict resolution approach could be used to engage students to study ‘Problems of democracy’.",
      "options": [
        "(A) is false but (B) is true.",
        "Both (A) and (B) are true.",
        "Both (A) and (B) are false.",
        "(A) is true but (B) is false."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (A) and (B) are true.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q71",
      "question": "Indian Constitution lays down ______________.",
      "options": [
        "norms for participation of people into social movements that seek to challenge the Government",
        "the national curriculum framework",
        "the basic laws or rules that have to be followed by everyone",
        "the structure of religious institutions"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the basic laws or rules that have to be followed by everyone",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q72",
      "question": "The objective of establishing Panchayati Raj institutions in India was to achieve __________",
      "options": [
        "Participatory governance",
        "Cultural homogeneity",
        "Democratic decentralization",
        "Religious diversity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q73",
      "question": "Which of the following topics are highly appropriate for middle level students ?\n(A) Contribution of Mahatma Gandhi in history.\n(B) Economic development of India.\n(C) Status of Women in present scenario.\n(D) Reasons for population growth.",
      "options": [
        " (A), (C) and (D) only",
        " (A) and (C) only",
        "(A) and (D) only",
        "(B), (C) and (D) only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": " (A) and (C) only",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q74",
      "question": "How can a Social Studies teacher develop social values among students ?\n(i) Developing sense of discipline\n(i) Behaving in the appropriate manner in school/class\n(iii) Asking Students to watch commercial movies\n(iv) Follow appropriate democratic values in class/school setting\nChoose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        "Only (iii) and (iv)",
        "Only (i) and (iii)",
        "Only (i), (ii) and (ii)",
        "Only (i), (ii) and (iv)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (i), (ii) and (iv)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q75",
      "question": "Which one of the following teaching methods are suitable to overcome the teaching challenges\nfaced in Social Sciences ?\n(A) From Specific to General (B) From Complex to General\n(C) From Known to Unknown (D) From Analysis to Synthesis\nChoose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        " (A), (B) and (D)",
        " (A), (B) and (C)",
        " (B), (C) and (D)",
        " (A), (C) and (D)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": " (A), (C) and (D)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q76",
      "question": "What does it mean to use the dialectic approach to teaching in the Social Science classroom?",
      "options": [
        "Using maps and atlases to enrich students' understanding of Geography",
        "Using dialogue between student and teacher as the main method of knowledge generation",
        "Using drama in the classroom to generate interest in students",
        "Using examples and analogies to clarify abstract concepts"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Using dialogue between student and teacher as the main method of knowledge generation",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q77",
      "question": "Which of the following questions asked by the teacher come under the category of exploratory and\ncritical questions ?\n(A) What is the southernmost part of the Himalayas called ?\n(B) Is the Sun a star ? Why ?\n(C) Why does more population reside in the Northern plains ?\n(D) Between which two countries is the Pak Water Treaty located ?",
      "options": [
        "(C) only",
        " (B) and (C)",
        "(B) only",
        " (A), (B), (C) and (D)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": " (B) and (C)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q78",
      "question": "Small workshops and factories prefer to employ casual workers because\n(A) state has already taken care of workers’ benefits\n(B) they can be fired without any prior notice\n(C) most of them are not literate\n(D) they could be paid lowest possible wages",
      "options": [
        "(A) and (C)",
        "(A) and (B)",
        "(B) and (D)",
        "(C) and (D)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "(B) and (D)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q79",
      "question": "Nelson Mandela spent 28 years of imprisonment along with thousands of black and coloured people.",
      "options": [
        "to raise voice against King and royal monarchy.",
        "for opposing apartheid and struggle against policies of segregation.",
        "to get punishment for offence.",
        "to get powerful positions in Government."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "for opposing apartheid and struggle against policies of segregation.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q80",
      "question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement about Gram Sabha?",
      "options": [
        "The Gram Sabha Secretary keeps a record of the Gram Sabha meeting proceedings.",
        "The work of the Gram Panchayat has to be approved by the Gram Sabha.",
        "The Gram Sabha Secretary is an elected person.",
        "The Gram Sabha Secretary is responsible for calling the meeting of Gram Sabha and Gram Panchayat."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The Gram Sabha Secretary is an elected person.",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q81",
      "question": "Which of the following emerged as an important religion in modern Adivasi history, during the nineteenth century ?",
      "options": [
        "Islam",
        "Buddhism",
        "Christianity",
        "Hinduism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Christianity",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q82",
      "question": "Consider the following statements (A) and (B).\n(A) The Government of India Act 1909, allowed for some elected representation system in India.\n(B) Through Government of India Act 1909 all adults were given the right to vote.\nChoose the correct option.",
      "options": [
        "Neither (A) nor (B) is true",
        "Only (A) is true",
        "Only (B) is true",
        "Both (A) and (B) are true"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (A) is true",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q83",
      "question": "Critical thinking is important in Social Science because :\n(A) It helps students to pass exam.\n(B) Itallows students to guess the correct answer\n(C) It helps students memorize information more easily\n(D) It prepare students for higher-level-thinking\n(E) It promotes problem-solving abilities\nChoose the correct option :",
      "options": [
        "Only (D) and (E)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "(A) (B)and (©)",
        "Only (A), (B), (C) and (E)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q84",
      "question": "Which would be the best teaching pedagogy to understand the trends in poverty in Indian States\nand Union Territories ?",
      "options": [
        "Brainstorming",
        "Field trip",
        "Debate",
        "Secondary data analysis"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Secondary data analysis",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q85",
      "question": "Which of the following questions assess the evaluation aspect of cognitive abilities ?\n\n(A) Poshan Abhiyan is an important programme to improve the nutrition level of Indian children.\nExamine the statement with evidences.\n\n(B) Colonial rule in India for two centuries left India with irreversible social change in India. Do\nyou agree with this statement ? Explain.\n\n(C) Describe the important features of Jan Dhan Yojana.\n\n(D) Poverty and unemployment in India has declined in the post 1991 India. Justify this statement.\n",
      "options": [
        "Only (C) and (D)",
        "Only (A) and (B)",
        "Only (A), (B) and (C)",
        "Only (B), (C) and (D)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only (A) and (B)",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q86",
      "question": "The teacher divides the children of her class into 4 groups and gives them to write the names of the sources of water and then discusses the sources of water with each group. Which of the following he/she is attempting first as part of the 5E approach to lesson plan?",
      "options": [
        "Engage",
        "Explore",
        "Evaluate",
        "Explain"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q87",
      "question": "A teacher wants students to understand the functioning of governmental bodies like Village Panchayat. Which of the following source of data collection will provide first-hand and authentic information ?",
      "options": [
        "Textbook",
        "Newspaper articles",
        "Field trip",
        "Biography"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Field trip",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q88",
      "question": "A belief that science requires a technical mind and girls and women are not capable of dealing with technical things signifies :",
      "options": [
        "Ignorance",
        "Stereotype",
        "Casteism",
        "literacy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Stereotype",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q89",
      "question": "In a field trip, which is the first skill to be developed among students?",
      "options": [
        "Reasoning skill",
        "Analytical skill",
        "Observation skill",
        "Experimentation skill"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Observation skill",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    },
    {
      "id": "SST-Dec24-Extracted-Verified-Q90",
      "question": "Rohit found that some children in his class could not explain the position of latitude and longitude\n\nlines on the map. What should Rohit do to help children acquire this competency ?",
      "options": [
        "Applied research",
        "Case study",
        "Empirical research",
        "Action research"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Action research",
      "explanation": "",
      "topic": "Unknown",
      "difficulty": "Medium",
      "attachments": []
    }
  ]
}